Guide to the Vernon L. Smith Papers, 1938-2019 RL.01220
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research and Writings, 1950-2009
  - Natural Resources and Utilities, 1969-2005 and undated; 24 boxes
    Material on electric utilities concerns the regulation and deregulation of electric companies and consists of articles, charts, clippings, drafts, and proposals. The principal regions researched include Australia, New Zealand, the United Kingdom, and the United States (Alaska, California, Illinois, New Mexico, and especially Arizona). The bulk of the files deals with work conducted at the Economics Science Lab, but other partners in this enterprise include the Arizona Corporation Commission (ACC), Federal Energy Regulation Commission (FERC), National Economic Research Associates (NERA). Department of Energy (DOE), National Science Foundation (NSF), Goldwater Institute, and various nationalized electric companies and government agencies.
    Material on smart markets concerns the network design for all utilities, but primarily electric and natural gas. Major folder groups deal with research conducted for the industry in Hungary and his book on smart markets.
    Material on natural gas consists of data, drafts, and research for his work entitled Experimental Auction Exchange for Pipeline Transmission Networks. Research was conducted in conjunction with FERC and the Energy Information Administration (EIA).
    Box 174 includes unsorted material acquired through the 2013 accession.
    - FERC Reactive Power, 2005; 36 files; approximately 20 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01220-SET-0003, Folder 1, Optical-disc RL01220-OP-0001)
      Text and presentation files.
    - Natural resources, 1970-2004 (Box 90-93)
    - Other files (Box 174)
    - Utilities, electric, 1969-2005 and undated (Box 93-107)
    - Utilities, natural gas, 1987-1994 and undated (Box 108-114)
      Includes data (charts, price regressions, and experimental auctions).
    - Utilities, smart markets, 1991-1994 and undated (Box 107-108)
  - Price Behavior, 1974-2000; 24 boxes
    Concerns the theory and institutions of auctions and bidding, with a focus on double auctions, Dutch auctions, English auctions, multiple unit auctions, and sealed bid auctions. Additional subjects include price controls and radio spectrum auctions.
    Arranged in original order.
    - Auctions, bidding, and lotteries (Box 115-128)
    - Auctions, 1985, 3 folders (Box 115)
    - Competitive Market Institutions: Double Auction vs. Sealed Bid Auctions, 1979-1981, 8 folders (Box 115)
    - A Comparision of Posted Offer and Double Auction Pricing Institutions, 1983 (Box 115)
    - Experimental Comparision of Alternative Rules for Competitive Market Exchange in Computerized Double Auction Markets, 1978-1980, 5 folders (Box 116)
    - First Price Auction Data; 2/6/91; Disk 001, 1991; 44 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials RL01220-SET-0001, Folder 1, Disk RL01220-FL3-0001)
      Text files.
    - OCS leasing and auctions, 2 folders (Box 116)
    - Why are not the Dutch and First Price Auctions Isomorphic? (Box 116)
    - Uncertainty and Partial Adjustment in Double Auction Markets, 1987 (Box 116)
    - Modifying Market Theories in the Light of Evidence, 1989-1990 (Box 116)
    - Auctions, The New Palgrave: a Dictionary of Economics, 1987-1991 (Box 117)
    - COT research proposal (Box 117)
    - Exogenous Uncertainty Increase the Bid-Ask Spread in the Continuous Double Auction (Box 117)
    - An Experimental Study of the Plato Computerized Double Auction Market Mechanism, 1978, 2 folders (Box 117)
    - Theory and Behavior of Single Object Auctions, 1980, 8 folders (Box 117)
    - Institutional Design for Electronic Trading, 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 117)
    - Auctions with a lambda variable, 3 folders (Box 118)
    - In search for the Winner's Curse, 1983 (Box 118)
    - Bidding and Auction Institutions: Experimental Results, 1974-1976, 3 folders (Box 118)
    - Dutch auctions
      - Articles, 2 folders (Box 118)
      - Charts, 2 folders (Box 118)
      - Notes (Box 118)
    - Incentives and Behavior in English, Dutch, and Sealed Bid Auctions, 2 folders (Box 118)
    - PDA protocol (Box 118)
    - The Discrete Bid First Price Auction, 1986 (Box 118)
    - Sealed bid auction theory and behavior (Box 118)
    - Auction bargaining mechanisms (Box 119)
    - Bidding institutions, notes, 2 folders (Box 119)
    - Bidding theory with risk preferences, 1983-1984, 2 folders (Box 119)
    - Properties auction (Box 119)
    - Treasury auctions, 2 folders (Box 119)
    - Burlington Northern, certificate test program, 1988, 2 folders (Box 119)
    - Various articles on auctions (Box 119)
    - Auctions and markets institutional design (Box 120)
    - Boundaries of competitive price theory, 2 folders (Box 120)
    - PDA, 8 folders (Box 120)
    - DOA, 2 folders (Box 120)
    - Sealed bid offer auctions (Box 120)
    - Back up charts, all auctions (Box 120)
    - Sequential english auction (Box 120)
    - Old transparencies, auctions (Box 120)
    - BPA, board of overseers, demo, 25 October 1991 (Box 120)
    - Oral bid, double, and offer auction charts (Box 120)
    - Dutch auctions (Box 120)
    - Hooker Lecture, McMaster University, 5 October 1988 (Box 120)
    - Single and multiple unit auctions (sealed bid) (Box 120)
    - Two commodities for PDA designs, 1983-1986, 3 folders (Box 120)
    - Multiple unit English clock auctions and assorted alternatives, 2 folders (Box 120)
    - Sealed bid offer auctions (Box 120)
    - Case studies, applied math, 1988 (Box 120)
    - PCS auction, 1994 (Box 121)
    - N-4 regressions (Box 121)
    - Lotteries (Box 121)
    - Individual Bidding with Simulated Competition, 1985 (Box 121)
    - Experiments
      - Hugg (Box 121)
      - Miller, 2 folders (Box 121)
      - Plott-Smith (Box 121)
    - Instructions, double auction (Box 121)
    - Q group proposal (Box 121)
    - Endogenous Entry and Exit in Common Value Auctions, 1991-1995, 4 folders (Box 121)
    - Posted offer and DA comparisons (Box 121)
    - Dutch-English auctions, first-second, charts (Box 122)
    - Discrimination vs. competition in sealed-bid auctions, charts (Box 122)
    - Designing Auction Institutions for Exchange, 1999 (Box 122)
    - Tests of a Heterogeneous Bidder's Theory of First Price Auctions, 3 folders (Box 122)
    - The Effects of Rent Asymmetries in Experimental Auction Markets, 1982 (Box 122)
    - Comparision of three auctions, Bratton (Box 122)
    - PLATO, 1978 and undated
      - PLATO and TUTOR manual (Box 122)
      - PLATO experiments, 2 folders (Box 122)
    - Bidding for a demand curve (Box 122)
    - Auctions and bidding, 1986 (Box 122)
    - Inducing Risk Neutral Preferences: an examination in a controlled market enviroment, 1986, 4 folders (Box 122)
    - Lottery regressions and charts (Box 122)
    - Charts of nonlinear regressions (Box 122)
    - The Sealed-Bid Mechanism: an experimental study, 1987 (Box 122)
    - Concurrent trading in two experimental markets with demand interdependence, 2000, 2 folders (Box 123)
    - Theory and Behavior in Auctions: effects of monetary rewards and decision cost, Irvine conference on decision theory (Box 123)
    - An Experimental Examination of the Walrasian Tatonnement Mechanism, 1996, 3 folders (Box 123)
    - Numerical Computation of First Price Auction with Heterogenous Risk, 1998 (Box 123)
    - Designing Auction Institutions: is Double Dutch best?, 1992, 3 folders (Box 123)
    - First price auctions
      - First price auction with fixed payment (charge) for winning (Box 123)
      - Rewards and behavior in first price auctions (Box 123)
      - Rewards, Experience and Decision Costs in First Price Auctions, 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 123)
      - Theory and Individual Behavior of First Price Auctions, 1986-1987, 7 folders (Box 124)
      - Theory and Misbehavior in First Price Auctions, 1989-1992, Folders 1-3 of 9 (Box 124)
      - Theory and Misbehavior in First Price Auctions, 1989-1992, Folders 4-9 of 9 (Box 125)
      - Data, 1991; 1 disk image derived from 3.5" floppy disk; approximately 3.1 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL01220-SET-0001)
        The disk is labled as: First Price Auction Data; 2/6/91; Disk 001.
    - Materials for reply to Kagel-Roth (Box 125)
    - Theory and Behavior of Multiple Unit Auctions, 1982-1984, Folders 1-4 of 17 (Box 125, Box 126)
    - Sealed bid auctions, Coppinger, 2 folders (Box 127)
    - An Experimental Comparison of Alternative Rules for Competitive Market Exchange, 1979 (Box 127)
    - A Test that Discriminates between Two Models of the Dutch-First Auction Non-Isomorphism, 1983, 2 folders (Box 127)
    - Bidding theory for heterogenous bidders, 2 folders (Box 127)
    - Combinatorial Auction Mechanism for Airport Time Slot Allocation, 3 folders (Box 127)
    - Bidding behavior in sealed bid discriminative auctions (Box 127)
    - A Comparison of Posted-Offer and Double Auction-Pricing Institutions, 1980-1983 (Box 128)
    - Experimental development of sealed bid auction theory, 2 folders (Box 128)
    - Combinatorial auction proposal, LECG/ESL/CALTECH, 1998 (Box 128)
    - Hand run call market sheets (Box 128)
    - Price controls (Box 128)
    - Radio spectrum auctions (Box 129)
    - Data, 1978-1983 (Box 129-138)
      Major folder groupings include PDA, S-bid, SDS, DFD, DSD, and Dutch auctions.
  - Other Writings, 1958-2008 and undated; 19 boxes
    Contains writings by Smith that do not belong in any of the other subject-based subseries.
    - American Economic Association, 1977-1981 (Box 139)
      - On replicability, 1981, 2 folders (Box 139)
      - Psychology and economics, 1977 (Box 139)
    - Anomalies, 1987, 2 folders (Box 139)
    - Behavioral economics research and the foundations of economics (Box 139)
    - Cobweb, 4 folders (Box 139)
    - Coursey, Don, charts (Box 139)
    - Consumer behavior, transparencies (Box 139)
    - On Creation vs. Discovery and The Origin of Predictable Behavior, 1984, 4 folders (Box 139)
    - Data, 1978-2000 (Box 187)
      Includes instructions, forms, and results of experiements. Mostly math and numbers (graphs/charts/tables; formulas/equations) compared to writing and words (let alone whole papers). Could probably be divided and placed under existing subject-specfic subseries by someone who knows more (such as experimental economics, price behavior, and game theory and strategic interactions).
    - Economics will never be the same (Box 139)
    - Evaluations of econometric models, 1981 (Box 139)
    - Humankind in Prehistory, Folders 1-4 of 8 (Box 139, Box 140)
    - Economic Principles in the Emergence of Humankind, 4 folders (Box 140)
    - On Emergence of Social and Political Institutions, 1985, 4 folders (Box 141)
    - Externalities, 9 folders (Box 141)
    - Fishing and Fisheries, 8 folders (Box 141)
    - Foundations of Experimental Political Economy, Plott and Smith (Box 141)
    - Fixed Cost Enviroments, 1996-1999, 5 folders (Box 142)
      Includes material on oligopolies and core allocation.
    - Free institutions proposal, 1981 (Box 142)
    - Frisco report, An Analysis of Rail Piggyback Transportation, 1958 (Box 142)
    - Health and history, notes and paper, 1994, 2 folders (Box 142)
    - Human Nature: An Economic Perspective, Daedalus, 2004 Fall (Box 142)
    - Hunting, 1973, 1985-1986, and undated, 10 folders (Box 143)
      Includes material on big animals, EPA conference, Hunting and Gathering Economies, and Economics of the primitive hunter culture with applications to pleistocene extinction and the rise of agriculture.
    - The Iraqi People's Fund, Wall Street Journal, 22 December 2003 (Box 143)
    - Man as an ecological factor within nature (Box 143)
    - Miscellaneous, 1951-2008 (Box 185, Box 186)
      Includes his M. A. thesis The Integrability Condition in the Pure Theory of Consumer's Behavior in hardcover and signed by Professor R. S. Howey and Dean Leonard Axe; correspondence with Cambridge University Press; and drafts and reprints of articles/chapters on Enron, stock market bubbles, risk aversion, experimental economics, deregulation of electric power, utility theory, trading, auctions, and microeconomics.
    - Motivation theory and behavior under the decision cost hypothesis, Smith and Walker (Box 143)
    - New Zealand, 1987-1991, 5 folders (Box 144)
      Includes material on colonization and the privatization and regulation of airports and telecommunications.
    - Plato nameset file (Box 144)
    - In Search of Predatory Pricing, Isaac and Smith, 1984-1985, Folders 1-3 of 6 folders (Box 144, Box 145)
    - Property rights, 1950, 1982, 1998, and undated, 15 folders (Box 145-146)
    - Public goods, 1970-1985, 2001-2004, and undated (Box 146-149)
    - Public goods, data (Box 149-152)
    - Rationality, 1984-1991, 7 folders (Box 153)
    - Recycling, 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 153)
    - Reflections on human actions after 50 years, 1999 (Box 154)
    - Siegal and other notes on EUT (Box 154)
    - Supply and demand equations, undated (Box 154)
    - Thoughts on Neo-classical, Contract Theories of State, 1980 (Box 154)
    - The Two Faces of Adam Smith, Southern Economic Journal, 1998, 7 folders (Box 154)
      Material derived in part from a revision to a previous paper concerning property rights.
    - Tournaments (Box 154)
    - Why Market Optimists Say This Bull Has Legs, Wall Street Journal, 23 May 2007 (Box 154)
  - Writings by Others, 1961-2009; 8 boxes
    Primarily contains reprints of articles by others on various topics of interest to Smith, which largely parallels the rest of the series: experimental economics, game theory and strategic decision making, markets, and price behavior.
    First two boxes are arranged alphabetically by author's last name. Remaining files are in original order.
    Box 174 includes additional unsorted writings by others acquired with the 2013 accession.
    - Isaac and Walker, Research in Experimental Economics, 1989; 13 files; less than 1 megabyte. (Digital-materials RL01220-SET-0001, Folder 1, Disk RL01220-FL5-0001)
      Text files; "On The Suboptimality of Voluntary Public Goods Provisions" by R. Mark Isaac and James M. Walker.
    - Writings by others (Box 155-161)
    - Writings by others (Box 174)
    - Writings by others, 1961-2009 (Box 187)
      Includes articles/chapters by Debreu, Durden-Smith, Hughes, Gordon, Malinvaud, Mendelson et al., Reiter, Spence, Hertwig and Ortman, Kimbrough, Levitt and List, Lopes, and Vickrey; a course pack for Competitive Decision Making from Raiffa; and publications of/from Fortune, Cato Institute, Heritage Foundation, and Immunology and Allergy Practice.
- Teaching, 1957-2019
  Covers Smith's lengthy teaching career, which included stops at Purdue University, Brown University, University of Massachusetts, University of Arizona, George Mason University, and Chapman University.
  Consists of two groupings: Courses and Departmental.
  Courses includes assigned readings by himself and others, course notes, transparencies, student experiments and essays, exam subjects, class lists, and graduate advising information.
  Departmental includes committee meetings concerning issues of honors candidates, fellowships, faculty, and promotion and tenure.
  Arranged roughly chronologically.
  Box 175 includes unsorted materials acquired through the 2013 accession.
  - Courses, 1957-1960s (Box 162)
  - Courses, 1960s-1972 (Box 163)
  - Courses, 1970-1976 (Box 164)
  - Courses, 1978-1983 (Box 165)
  - Courses, 1984-1988 (Box 166)
  - Courses, 1988-1992 (Box 167)
  - Courses, 1992-1994 (Box 168)
  - Courses, 1995-1998 (Box 169)
  - Courses, 1999-2006 and undated (Box 170)
  - Courses, 2002-2019 (Box 188)
    Includes syllabi, readings, and student papers from ECON and LAW courses at George Mason and Chapman.
  - Courses, undated (Box 171)
  - Departmental materials, 1977-1997 and undated (Box 171-172)
  - Economic Systems Design materials; other proposals; general lecture notes (Box 175)